# Matteo Guida

🛮 00 (49) 176 3077 0855 | 🗷 matteo.guidaa@gmail.com | 📠 linkedin.com/in/matteo-guida-7872341b3/ | ♀ GitHub

## Personal Profile

Masters Student Graduate in Speech and Language Processing at the University of Konstanz (Germany) with a solid theoretical background in (computational) linguistics and knowledge in Deep Learning and statistical methods, and practical industry experience in the field of Natural Language Processing.

#### **Education**

University of Konstanz Konstanz Konstanz, Germany

Masters in Speech and Language Processing

Oct 2021 - Current

- · Main track: Natural Language Processing
- Relevant Courses: Corpus Linguistics with Python, Deep Learning with Python, Machine Language Processing, Statistics with R, Linguistics, Finite State Morphology
- Average GPA: 1.2 (1 being the highest)
- Expected date of graduation: February 2024
- · Thesis: Automatic Hate Speech Detection in Italian Text using Deep Learning Techniques (BERT and Llama)

University of Trieste Trieste, Italy

**Bachelor in Applied Linguistics** 

Oct 2018 - July 2021

- Graduated with 108 out of 110
- Thesis: "German in a non-European multilingual context: the case of Namibia".

Liceo Galileo Galilei Civitavecchia, Italy

Italian-French High School

Sept 2013 - July 2018

- Graduated with 100 out of 100
- Received both the Italian and French high school diploma. Classes were taught in Italian, French, Spanish and English.

## **Work Experience**

DHL Group Bonn, Germany

Working Student, Natural Language Processing

September 2023 - January 2024

- Fine-tuning of LLMs for domain specific content generation, entity recognition and text summarization, Generative Question-Answering with LangChain, Custom Machine Translation & Evaluation, Data pre-processing, cleaning and annotation
- Technical Skills: Machine Learning, Kubernets (Kubeflow), Azure, Large Language Models, Langchain, Generative AI, Deep Learning for NLP, Git, RestAPIs, AWS

**Deutsche Post DHL Group** 

Bonn, Germany

Intern in Linguistic Data Management

March 2023 - August 2023

- Data Cleaning & Annotation, Data-Specific Customized NER Models for terminology extraction, evaluation of models, (Neural) Machine Translation
- **Technical Skills:** Programming in Python, NLP libraries, Deep Learning, Git, RestAPIs, AWS, Google Cloud AutoML, Prodigy, Tableau

University of Konstanz Konstanz, Germany

Teaching Assistant for the MA Course "Machine Language Processing"

Oct 2022 - Feb 2023

- This course offers both a theoretical and practical introduction into Natural Language Processing and covers a variety of fundamental topics in the field of Speech and Language Processing (including Regular Expressions, Text Pre-Processing, supervised and unsupervised ML, information extraction, dialogue systems) and a practical introduction to Linux.
- My tasks: Weekly tutorial to help students with Linux-related issues (useful command lines and RegEx for computational linguists) and theoretical NLP concepts, correction and grading of assignments.

University of Konstanz Konstanz, Germany

Student Research Assistant

Nov 2022 - Feb 2023

- · Project on sarcasm detection which aims at finding what contexts might trigger (or not) sarcasm and if multimodal clues also play a role in it.
- Technical Skills: Programming in Python and R (Data Cleaning & Preparation), Excel, evaluation of NLP models, Deep Learning (Word Embeddings, BERT, Transformers)

DECEMBER 26, 2023

# Skills & Knowledge \_\_\_\_\_

**Programming** Python (Pandas, PyTorch, NumPy, Scikit-learn, Spacy, NLTK, Core NLP, Stanza, Gensim, TensorFlow, Keras), R

Miscellaneous Linux, Shell (Bash/Zsh), \(\mathbb{E}\)FX(Overleaf/R Markdown), Microsoft Office, Git

Machine Learning Neural Networks, Linear Regression, Logistic Regression, TF-IDF, evaluation metrics, Word Embeddings (Word2Vec, GloVe)

**& Others** Deep Learning architectures (CNNs, RNNs, LSTMs, Transformers), Prodigy, Tableau, APIs

# Workshops\_

#### **Basque Summer Tutorial in Language Documentation**

Larrau/Tardets-Sorholus, France

16 - 26 Aug 2022

- Summer School in collaboration with the University of Bordeaux, the French-German University, the University of Konstanz, IKER, the University of Pau and Pays de l'Adour, and the CNRS.
- Conceptual, technical and ethical issues in Language Documentation and endangered languages, along with actual fieldwork in-situ (conducting interviews and analyzing data)
- Research Proposal: an analysis of vowels production in Zuberoan Basque
- Technical Skills: Praat, ELAN, Audactiy, R

## Languages \_\_\_\_\_

**Italian** Native proficiency

EnglishFrenchFull professional proficiencyGermanSpanishFull professional proficiencyFull professional proficiency

### Interests\_\_\_\_\_

Linux, Linguistics, Natural Language Processing, Ethical AI